<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-14T14:48:25-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Project_data_science</title><subtitle>Data is the new oil.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Milestone 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data/science/project/2023/10/04/milestone-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Milestone 1" /><published>2023-10-04T15:25:05-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T15:25:05-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data/science/project/2023/10/04/milestone-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data/science/project/2023/10/04/milestone-1.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="question-1">Question 1</h2>

<p>…content…</p>

<h2 id="question-2">Question 2</h2>

<p>…content…</p>

<hr />
<h2 id="5simple-visualizations">5.Simple Visualizations</h2>

<h3 id="question-1-comparing-shot-types">Question 1: Comparing Shot Types</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>I chose the 2016 season (including both the regular season and playoffs) to produce a figure that compares shot types across all teams. In analyzing the data, it becomes clear that the most dangerous type of shot is the “deflected” shot, with the highest goal percentage of 19.8%. This suggests that deflected shots have a significantly higher chance of resulting in a goal compared to other shot types.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>On the other hand, the most common type of shot is the “wrist shot,” as indicated by the highest bar in the histogram. The reason I chose this figure is that it provides a straightforward visual representation of the shot and goal counts for each shot type, allowing us to easily compare their quantities and ratios. It’s a valuable tool for understanding which shot types are both frequent and effective in scoring goals.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/Image/Simple_Visualizations/Q5-1_shot_type_histogram.png" alt="" /></p>

<h3 id="question-2-relationship-between-shot-distance-and-goal-chance">Question 2: Relationship between Shot Distance and Goal Chance</h3>

<ul>
  <li>In ice hockey matches, it is generally observed that the closer the shot distance to the goal, the higher the probability of scoring. This is because when a player is closer to the goal, the goalkeeper’s defensive range is reduced, increasing the chances of successfully putting the puck into the net. As evident in the chart, it is clear that the scoring probability is significantly higher for shot distances less than 70 feet when compared to shot distances greater than 70 feet. This trend remained consistent across the years 2018, 2019, and 2020. I opted for a line plot graph as it provides a direct visualization of how the likelihood of scoring changes with varying shot distances.
<img src="/Image/Simple_Visualizations/Q5-2_shot_distance_vs_goal_chance_2018.png" alt="" />
<img src="/Image/Simple_Visualizations/Q5-2_shot_distance_vs_goal_chance_2019.png" alt="" />
<img src="/Image/Simple_Visualizations/Q5-2_shot_distance_vs_goal_chance_2020.png" alt="" /></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="question-3-goal-percentage-by-shot-distance-and-type">Question 3: Goal Percentage by Shot Distance and Type</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>In this analysis, I utilized data from the year 2016, including both regular season and playoff games. The figure reveals that there isn’t a single shot type that stands out as the most dangerous across all shot distances. Instead, each shot type has its own optimal goal-scoring range.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s evident that when the shot distance is less than 10 feet, the “wrap-around” shot type appears to be the most dangerous, as it boasts the highest average goal-scoring probability in that range. In the 10 to 20 feet distance range, “Tip-in” or “Deflected” shots are preferable choices. When the shot distance extends to the 20 to 40 feet range, “Snap Shot” becomes a more effective option. For distances greater than 40 feet but less than 70 feet, “Slap Shot” appears to be a favorable choice. However, when the shot distance exceeds 70 feet, the goal-scoring probability for all shot types decreases significantly.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="can-not-find-image">Can not find Image</h1>
<p><img src="/Image/Simple_Visualizations/Q5-3_" alt="" /></p>

<hr />
<h2 id="6advanced-visualization">6.Advanced visualization</h2>

<h3 id="question-1-export-html-plot">Question 1. Export html plot</h3>
<ul>
  <li>The shot map visualization are stored <a href="/Image/Advanced_visualization/shot_map_visualization.html">here</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="question-2-discusss-from-shot-map">Question 2. Discusss from shot map</h3>
<ul>
  <li>The main idea here is to measure the frequency of shots from specific positions for each team compared to the league average. This measure helps highlight areas where a team may be particularly strong or weak compared to the average league.</li>
  <li>For example, if Team A has a higher shot rate in front of the net, it suggests that Team A is likely to take shots at close range compared to the average league.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="question-3-discuss-about-the-team-colorado-avalanche">Question 3. Discuss about the team <em>Colorado Avalanche</em></h3>
<ul>
  <li>In season 2016-2017, the Colorado Avalanche had dark blue in front of the net, which means that this team took fewer shots compared to the average league. We can assume that the forwards of this team are bad at the shot. As a result, this team final at the lowest ranking of the league.
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2016/Colorado%20Avalanche.jpg" alt="" title="Shot map of Colorado Avalanche in season 2016-2017" width="300px" height="300px" /></li>
  <li>In season 2020-2021, the Colorado Avalanche have a dark red in the middle of the offensive zone, which mean that this team takes a lot of shot. In other words, the forwards of this team are good at controlling the match and shot. Finally, this team takes the highest position in the standings.
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2020/Colorado%20Avalanche.jpg" alt="" title="Shot map of Colorado Avalanche in season 2020-2021" width="300px" height="300px" /></li>
  <li>The analysis and final results make sense.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="question-4-comparision-between-buffalo-sabres-and-tampa-bay-lightning">Question 4. Comparision between <em>Buffalo Sabres</em> and <em>Tampa Bay Lightning</em></h3>
<ul>
  <li><em>Buffalo Sabres</em>:
    <ul>
      <li>From the 2018-2020 seasons, this team had a dark blue area in front of the net. This means that this team can not approach the opponent’s goal and take a shot.</li>
      <li>Although the Buffalo Sabres have some dark red area in the map (in the year 2018-2019), it is far from the net. It is a long-range shot, which is not really an effective strategy.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2018/Buffalo%20Sabres.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /> 
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2019/Buffalo%20Sabres.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /> 
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2020/Buffalo%20Sabres.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Tampa Bay Lightning</em>:
    <ul>
      <li>This team had a dark red area in front of the net during 2018-2020. This means that this team control the match and take a lot of shot to the opponent’s net.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2018/Tampa%20Bay%20Lightning.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /> 
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2019/Tampa%20Bay%20Lightning.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /> 
<img src="/Image/Advanced_visualization/2020/Tampa%20Bay%20Lightning.jpg" alt="" width="300px" height="300px" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="science" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Question 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/04/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2023-10-04T15:25:05-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T15:25:05-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/04/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/04/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry></feed>